Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we answer a wide
variety of your questions,
like the best way
to treat insomnia,
or information on how
to lower your cholesterol,
and whether or not you
can eat too many beans.
Hello, this is Dr. Michael Greger coming to
you live from my stationary treadmill because
so many people complained that I was making
them seasick. I don't want to make people
sick—that's kind of the antithesis of what
I'm trying to do. Let's get to your questions.
“First one up is nutritionally, for weight
loss and longevity, are peanuts more like
nuts or legumes? And which nuts have the highest
concentration of plant sterols to bring down LDL?”
Nutritionally, peanuts are very similar to tree
nuts. In terms of weight loss, they have a very
similar caloric density. In terms of longevity,
walnuts really beat all other tree nuts as well
as peanuts. And I don't think peanut butter works
at all. Does silica prevent AGEs? No, not that I
know of, nor would it boost collagen. I do have a
webinar on collagen-boosting foods; check it out.
“Should the government tax high saturated fat
foods?” Whether it should or whether it could—so,
there was a... I do have videos talking about
the Danish meat tax, which was so effective
that the animal agriculture lobby made sure
it did not last very long, but just as we were
starting to see significant public health
benefits, unfortunately, it was repealed.
“Any tips on repopulating my gut after a course
of antibiotics?” Well, probiotics—taking probiotic
supplements actually makes things worse. It
actually delays the rebalancing of your gut flora,
which is something that I discovered in
researching How Not to Age. Check out my
probiotics chapter. All we can do is just
start feeding... I mean, there are certain
antibiotics that absorb in the small intestine
and don't really affect much in the gut, but if
you're experiencing gastrointestinal symptoms,
make sure to get lots of prebiotics to feed
the stragglers. You know, we're not sterilizing
the gut; your gut microbes may just take a hit,
so you feed them lots of good food, and they
will be fruitful and multiply on their own.
“Are there any health benefits you can get from
coffee but not from green tea?” Absolutely. So,
coffee has chlorogenic acid, the
autophagy-boosting antioxidant,
which green tea does not have. Three cups of
coffee a day decrease all-cause mortality by
13%, while three cups of tea a day decrease it
by 24%, but by a different mechanism—actually,
ironically, a pro-oxidant mechanism, rallying
our antioxidant defenses in an interesting
"that which doesn't kill us makes us
stronger" hormetic mechanism. Anyway,
they both work through different mechanisms, so we
would assume it would be an additive effect. So,
eat both or drink both. I started out
with coffee; now I'm drinking tea.
Next up, “any advice to help with sleep—not
just falling asleep but staying asleep?”
Absolutely. So, treating insomnia is all
about sleep hygiene and sleep conditioning,
and I think I've talked about five rules of
each in the sleep chapter of How Not to Age,
and I think the sleep chapter of How Not to
Diet also has the same information. Also,
warm baths—either foot baths or full-body
baths or showers before going to bed,
even just wearing warm socks at night—improve
sleep through an interesting mechanism which I
talk about in How Not to Age. Check it out—go
to your local public library and check it out.
Okay, next up: “I've taken amla—amla's
dried Indian gooseberry powder—and it
lowered cholesterol levels by about
10%.” That's great! “What if there
was one thing to lower high blood pressure?
What would it be?” Hibiscus tea, probably,
or ground flaxseed would be my two best bets.
But less than a teaspoon a day of ground black
sesame seeds also drops systolic blood pressure
by about eight points. Sustaining that alone
could decrease your risk of stroke by
about a quarter. How exciting is that?
Okay, Phil Hampton says, “what are my thoughts on
echinacea?” I talk about echinacea being useless
in terms of upper respiratory infections. I've
not heard of anything about group streptococcus
and echinacea, but if it's being—I mean, the
thing that we thought had the greatest evidence
base for it was upper respiratory infections,
and it turns out it doesn't even work for that.
Bonnie says, “how much fat should one have
at each meal to get sufficient nutrition?”
This questioner, what Bonnie is asking, is talking
about the absorption of fat-soluble nutrients. So,
if you eat a meal without any fat in it—like a
salad with no nuts or seeds or avocado with a
fat-free dressing—you are not going to maximally
absorb all the fat-soluble phytonutrients,
like all those carotenoid nutrients that are so
beneficial, like the beta carotene in greens,
etc. It does not take much; I have a video
about that where I give exact values,
but it was just a few—like a few
walnuts or a quarter of an avocado,
if I remember correctly. But check out that
video. And yes, soybeans certainly—chickpeas
are low in fat, but soybeans may have enough fat.
But you know, you've got to sprinkle flaxseeds
onto your food anyway—ground flaxseeds are part
of my Daily Dozen—so that's another great way
to make sure you have just enough fat to boost
the absorption of your fat-soluble nutrients.
“Sarcoma with paravertebral invasion—just got
diagnosed with that.” That's not good. So,
sarcoma is a cancer of connective tissues.
Oh, that's a fantastic question. So,
what can I actually do? That is the subject
of what I hope is going to be my next book,
if the publisher agrees—a book on cancer. So,
I'll be doing daily cancer protocols for all 16
or so cancers that kill 5,000 Americans or more.
Although sarcoma may not actually make the list,
fingers crossed. So, I just don't know, but there
certainly are foods that can improve survival for
different types of cancer—different foods for
different cancers. But sarcoma is not one I've
looked into and may not look into for the book.
I don't think that actually made the list. I
think the 16th was melanoma. So, cancers more
rare than that, killing fewer Americans, will
not make the list, unfortunately. Already it's
going to be a massive book with the Daily Dozen.
“I get all my vitamin needs except for one—I
only get 300 milligrams of choline versus the
RDA of 550. I can't eat soy and don't want to
eat more broccoli. Should I supplement?” No,
you shouldn't supplement. Just type in "choline"
on NutritionFacts.org and look at its effects on
organ function. Choline is an essential nutrient,
but you don't want to get too much
because bad bacteria can turn choline
into trimethylamine, which is oxidized by the
liver and wreaks havoc in the body. But you
should be able to get all the choline you need
from whole foods without taking supplements.
“Are there health issues associated
with silicone cooking utensils?”
Not that I've seen. It's not something I've
looked at particularly, but I did do a lot
of videos on cooking utensils and pots
and pans. I assume if something was bad,
it would have popped up. But I have not seen
anything offhand. If you do a PubMed search and
something comes up, send it my way because
I cook with silicone, so I'd want to know.
"My books are life-changing," says Fernanda. Thank
you! “Is a calcium supplement from algae better?”
No, no, no, no, no. We should not be supplementing
for calcium. It's not particularly effective,
it's not safe, and regardless of what kind—it's
just a scam. And in this case, a dangerous scam,
because you're getting too much of a calcium spike
in your bloodstream. Check out my videos for more.
Fernanda's back—would I recommend statins
for someone whose LDL was 190? Oh,
Jesus. 90 is good. No, but 190 is way too
high, especially with a high LP(a), which
is largely genetically determined, so you need
to get your LDL absolutely as low as possible,
certainly under 70 for primary prevention. I would
go on the Portfolio Diet, which is a plant-based
diet with particular foods that lower LDL
cholesterol. See how far you can take diet, and if
you can't get it down to target, then absolutely
talk to your physician about prescribing drugs.
“People at Mastering Diabetes claim that dietary
fat—not just any dietary fat, but particularly
saturated fat—causes insulin resistance. In
their diet, they restrict fat to 10-15%. Is that
necessary?” Well, that certainly is more typical
of how our species evolved—getting about 10%
of calories from fat. But insulin resistance is
really a problem with saturated fat in the context
of excess calorie intake. But yeah, different fats
are kind of a mixture of various fats, and so,
for example, there's some saturated fat in nuts,
even though nuts have an overall benefit. That's
because of all the other wonderful things in nuts.
But I think if you just restrict saturated fat,
which is in meat, dairy, and junk food, you
should be able to reverse your insulin resistance.
“Do I need to worry about pH value when
making a DIY vitamin C serum?” Oh, you know,
I wouldn't mix the vitamin C and niacinamide
together in a serum. I would do them separately
just because... yeah, I don't know what the
vitamin C would be doing to the niacinamide.
“Fascinated by longevity research?
Wild blueberry”—well, wild blueberry,
you would like my new book. “What specific
blood markers”—oh, interesting. Yeah,
so there are all sorts of interesting measures
of biological aging. There are lots of companies
trying to fight it out to be the best. Probably
the kind of following the epigenetic clock is the
most well-validated, but I'm not sure what
commercial tests are available. I know
what tests are used in a laboratory setting,
but not sure what's available commercially.
“Hello,” says Niall. “I was wondering if
I could get your insight on artificial
sweeteners, like sucralose.” I’ve got videos on
sucralose. Yes, there is a health concern—it has
to do with causing dysbiosis in the gut.
You know, sucralose manufacturers like to
brag about how their artificial sweetener
doesn't get absorbed into the bloodstream,
so therefore it's safe. But guess what? If
it doesn't get absorbed into the bloodstream,
what does it do? It ends up in the colon,
where it mucks with our microbiome. So,
don't do it. If you want to see the science,
just type in "sucralose" on NutritionFacts.org.
“Are puffed grains unhealthy?” Yeah, puffing,
as well as kind of explosion-extrusion,
and all sorts of things to make breakfast
cereals—it's just ways to kind of increase
the glycemic index, which is not something
we want. So yeah, I would avoid that,
even if they're whole grains. There are better
ways to get your grains, like whole intact grains.
Victoria says her husband, 63, has been
following a whole-food, plant-based diet for
six years, but his total cholesterol is still
high. Oh my God, LDL is way too high. Well,
so, you know, a lot of people claim they're on
a whole-food, plant-based diet, but are eating
vegan junk food that has tropical oils like
coconut oil or something. That'd be the first
thing to check. But if you really are eating whole
foods and your LDL is that extraordinarily high,
I would try the Portfolio Diet, as I talked
about before. David Jenkins at the University
of Toronto—that's the best diet for maximally
lowering cholesterol. But if you can't get it down
to target, then you need to figure out another
way. There are lots of things you can take that
also lower cholesterol, like amla and things like
that. But again, if you can't do it by diet, you
have to get it down some way, and that can include
drugs—higher-dose drugs, multiple drugs, whatever
it takes to get your LDL down, which is a primary
risk factor for the number one killer in women.
Wealthy says, “what do we think about
Peter Rogers?” Never heard of him. A
more radical version of me? How funny. Now
I want to Google him—never heard of him.
“Can I roast nuts on low temperature
to avoid forming acrylamides?” It's not
the acrylamides we worry about in nuts.
Acrylamides are more of a concern with
high-heat cooking of carbohydrates like
crackers, French fries, and potato chips.
The nut roasting causes the formation
of advanced glycation end-products. I
think it starts occurring at like 250°F,
so it's not really the roasting of nuts,
but if you can keep your nuts under that
temperature, you'll likely keep your AGEs low.
I find them easier to chew than raw. Raw—I
don't know why raw nuts would be hard to chew,
like raw walnuts—are they hard to chew?
“Can I eat too much protein from beans? I hear
doctors say more than a cup a day of beans”—well,
why can't you eat more than a cup a day? In fact,
I recommend in my Daily Dozen a cup and a
half—right, three servings a day of legumes,
with a serving being a half-cup. How many
beans can we eat? Why would you be hurting
your kidneys? Beans do not hurt your kidneys.
In fact, the recommendation is to switch over
to plant protein for protecting chronic kidney
failure patients—to protect one's kidneys by
reducing animal protein intake. If you have
extremely poor kidney function, then they may
want to decrease your protein overall, but you
need to talk to a renal dietitian, definitely.
Anthony ate a whole-food, plant-based
diet for four months. Oh my God,
lost 75 pounds—congratulations! But then, in four
months, gained back 40 pounds. So, I talk about
what is behind the stalling of weight loss and
gaining back weight in How Not to Diet. Go to
your local public library, get How Not to Diet,
and go to that chapter. Sorry to hear that.
Isabelle says she's a huge fan—that's nice. Can
I advise what a type 1 diabetic should eat to
prevent diabetic bone disease? I don't think of
diabetes causing bone disease, but I mean, type 1
diabetes can be certainly serious. You know, the
Defeating Diabetes or Mastering Diabetes folks
know a lot about type 1 diabetes, so basically
you're trying to improve insulin resistance just
to make your body more sensitive to the insulin
that you are injecting. But you will be injecting,
or your child will be injecting, insulin
for their whole life—critically important
to maintain... yeah, primarily to not bottom out
and have life-threatening hypoglycemia. So yeah,
it's very important to work very closely with your
medical professionals to make sure that they keep
their blood sugar levels stable. We can do
that by improving insulin sensitivity so
you can get into a regular regimen of knowing
exactly how much insulin you need every day.
“How long to microwave 1.5 ounces of mushrooms
to make sure the polyphenol oxidase is gone?”
This is such a high-level question—I
love it! What is the optimum amount of
mushrooms to eat every day? I hear too
much is a waste. Huh, I don't think so;
I've certainly never heard that. No, no, eat as
many mushrooms as you want! Oh, speaking of which,
I just made some pasta sauce and totally forgot my
maitake mushrooms—I'm totally going to add some. I
did a long Q&A talking about polyphenol oxidases.
Didn't I talk about how much? Don't quote me—go
to the video where I actually show the data on
how many seconds it takes—it does not take much.
What are my thoughts about the NIH report on
a study saying spermidine can cause stroke?
I've never heard of that. Alright, now you got
me. I am typing it into PubMed as we speak...
serum spermidine in relation to stroke...
so it's not talking about taking spermidine;
it's talking about serum spermidine. But serum
spermidine is linked to lower all-cause mortality,
which is the most important thing. It is the
most predictive nutrient. Following hundreds
of individuals between the ages of 45 and
64, they found 146 components of people's
diets, and spermidine was the single most
associated with longevity. So, presumably, that
would wash out any stroke effect if there even is
a stroke effect. And they're certainly not talking
about taking it as a supplement, so there’s a
possibility of reverse causation or whatever. But
that is totally interesting—I'm going to look into
that when I do my spermidine update. But so far,
I would stick to my recommendation because of
all-cause mortality—that's the most important
thing. But I will look into it—thank you so
much for letting me know, that's exciting!
How do I explain ApoB and how it compares
to LDL for atherosclerosis risk? So,
ApoB is a protein that's kind of part of LDL,
but it's also a protein found in other kinds
of lipoprotein conglomerates. But LDL continues
to be recommended as the best marker. Testing
companies are always trying to come up with fancy
methods to test, but LDL is just so dirt cheap,
they're not making a lot of money on it.
But it's hard to really beat out LDL for
predicting survival and cardiovascular
disease risk. I would stick with LDL.
“If someone ate a pure carnivore diet, how long
until they would develop scurvy, the vitamin
C deficiency disease?” Well, it depends. If you
ate raw meat—I don't recommend eating raw meat,
don't recommend eating cooked meat either—but raw
meat has some vitamin C. That's how, you know,
the Inuit could survive on eating whale carcasses
without much plant food during the winter months.
How long does it take to develop scurvy? I
have videos about it—I think it just takes a
couple of weeks. In fact, I talk about it in
my fasting video. Anyway, it takes a while,
but scurvy is not the reason why you don't want
to do the carnivore diet. You don't want to do
the carnivore diet because of the saturated
fat intake, the cholesterol intake, etc.
“If you have elevated liver enzymes, can the liver
heal if you drink non-alcoholic beer and wine?”
Well, the reason your liver enzymes are high is
because they've been suffering alcoholic damage
from the alcohol. If you stop drinking alcohol,
can your liver heal? Absolutely. Your liver has
a remarkable ability to regenerate unless it's
really far along. So yes, stop drinking alcohol.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.